Meeting Agenda/Minutes

Attending

Manchester: Franck, Katy, Jits EBI: Thomas, Hamish, Eric

Apologies

Carole, Rodrigo

Minuting

Franck

Agenda

Actions from Previous Meeting

EBI - Register domain name “biocatalogue.org” and contact the Korean institute about “biocatalog.org” Not sure if Rodrigo contacted the Korean

Eric/Hamish/Thomas - Join the myexperiment skype chats Done

Eric/Franck - Produce matrix of service types against bioinformatics domain coverage and properties, to generate a representative set of services to pilot with. Done

Everybody - Dump all possible attributes/information that could be collected about services on to the mailing list in order to help Eric/Franck enhance the proposed curation model. Done

Jiten/Eric/Thomas - Setup a myExperiment environment at EBI and walk through myExperiment codebase. Done

Everyone - Decide the exact date of the next telecom meeting; preferably week starting the 26/05. next meeting on Tuesday 10/06

Franck - select representative KEGG services to use. Done

Franck - send out definition of “semantic type” to mailing list for further discussion and refinement. Done, definition is in the model

Eric/Franck - work on the metatada levels for bronze/silver/gold/platinum compliance. Done, model is on the wiki

Round-table

Franck: worked on the platinum annotation model from which they've derived the bronze, silver and gold. These models are on the wiki. Selected a number of broadly used bioinformatics web services. will now describe selected services using the model.

Jits: help Thomas and Eric to set up myexperiment code base at EBI. will meet Thomas and Eric to discuss the code base

Katy: Attending a Web service metadata meeting in Australia, the report of the meeting is on the list and the wiki. discuss the annotation model with Franck

Eric: worked on the annotation model, Familiarising himself with myExperiment code base. Joined myExperiment 5pm chat. Will look at the back end database.

Thomas: Set up a private myExperiment code base at EBI. Joined myExperiment 5pm chat.

Hamish: Encouraging service providers to describe their services.

Upcoming Meetings

Meetings and deadlines that are coming up

Any Other Business (AOB)

We all agree to have at this stage weekly meeting. The next one is next Tuesday 3-5pm Everybody should start writing 'stories' about what they do Franck: looking for example of services with security/licensing/restrictions issues to use as example. Biocatalogue back end: Ruby on Rails or Java? Jits said Java would be better. Minutes

New actions

Everybody: read the services matrix and check out the annotations models Franck: post on the list example of stories Thomas: start advertising biocatalogue on the new domain

Previous/Next Minutes

Previous meeting: PhoneMeeting_13_05_2008 

Next meeting: PhoneMeeting_13_06_2008

Date: Tuesday 27th Jan 2008

Time: 15:00-16:00 (UK)

Telcon No: 08445805588

Pin: 70503010

Attending

Manchester: Franck, Jits, Carole

EBI: Thomas, Eric, Rodrigo

Apologies

Minuting

Agenda

Hackathon summary

Actions from the last telcon

Progress with the pilot

Progress of 20 Questions (to clarify user requirements)

Updating the BioCatalogue public wiki and announcement to friends list

AOB

Actions from Previous Meeting

Franck : Provide an example of a semantically annotated service(using the SAWSDL model).

Thomas: investigate 'home' link on the public wiki.

Jits/Thomas/Eric: create developer section on the wiki.

Franck: read through the revised requirements and planning doc and update the private wiki roadmap accordingly. Then after approval copy it to the public wiki.

Franck: make an announcement about latest changes to schedule to the friends list.

Action all : update the 20 questions section on the wiki

Action Jits/Eric : Investigate how to add some form of classification of the services

Action David/Carole/Steve : Review the wiki pages intended for general public. It is important to free the public wiki of internal terminology

Action Franck : Put up a service classification draft on the wiki

Action Jits/Thomas/Eric/Franck : Prepare for the hackathon in Manchester.

Minutes

Minutes from the hackathon: F2F Hackathon 21-22-23 January @ Manchester
Other item we discuss during the meeting:

Test scripts need to go through a validation process

Policy Identification needed in relation:

taking down service

curation best practices

tagging best practices

annotation best practices

Annotation

how mutable should annotations be? Allow user to make changes to their own annotations. Avoid over engineering the functionality

delegation of privileges to other users to make changes to services(annotations) owned by the delegator

most important thing is to keep the annotations up to date, that is what most users care about

20 Questions

questions on statistics in the system, how many…

questions on metrics, status

question relations

questions on editing and maintaining (house keeping) entries in the catalogue

Advisory board meeting in March @ Manchester

New Actions

Upcoming Meetings

AOB

There will be a demo at the Strategic Advisory Board Meeting in February

There is potential for collaboration with Microsoft. Initial discussions on-going with Carole

Jit doing a presentation on BioCatalogue on the 29th

Previous/Next Meetings

Previous meeting: Phone Conference Meeting on Jan 20 2009

Next meeting: Phone Conference Meeting on Feb 03 2009

The BioCatalogue work plan for 2011

For 2011 we plan to work on the following features, which will be prioritised based on users' feedback and requests. To have your say, please join the BioCatalogue-Friends Mailing List

Functional Units (FU)

Functional/task view over web services

FUs as conﬁgurations and compositions of underlying service operations that can then be described, annotated and searched for

Improving search capabilities and user interface

“People who searched for this also searched for x”

Consolidating the filtering and search user interfaces

Improving the annotations mechanism

Incorporating the EDAM ontology

Richer annotation fields (choice-based, semantic chooser, suggestions, etc.

Better curation reports and tools for expert curators

Improving the curation dashboard and annotating features

“Try it now” service functionality

Ability to test and play with a service within the BioCatalogue interface e.g. run SOAP operations or REST endpoints directly

Curator community features

Improving support for curators and building a community of curators e.g. curator invites and reward badges

Annotation status bar: a status bar to display the overall annotation status of a service.

More customisable and brand-able system

More and more people are deploying their own instance using the BioCatalogue software

Need to make the software more customisable as well as more robust

Need to make it easier to configure images, styles, colours etc

Integration with myExperiment

Services from BioCatalogue displayed in myExperiment so users of myExperiment can browse them.

Workflows in myExperiment will have links to the relevant services, with metadata and monitoring status pulled from BioCatalogue.

Better service filtering and ranking

Ability to filter or rank service based on annotations, quality, curators etc.

Service versions

Support for different versions of a service (i.e.: SOAP and REST versions of a single service).

Notifications and news feeds per service

RSS/ATOM feeds for services, providing information on all activity on a service within the BioCatalogue.

Annotations Plugin

Available here: http://github.com/jits/annotations (with full documentation)

IMPORTANT: you have to create a controller and model for annotations again in your app (but leaving them blank is fine though they can be used to extend the original ones from the plugin. AND use require_dependency (see examples of usage in BioCatalogue).

Controller depends on the presence of login_required, logged_in? and current_user methods (these should be in your application controller). The current_user method MUST return nil if no user is currently logged in.

Whilst running in development mode, if you get an error such as: ”A copy of ApplicationController has been removed from the module tree but is still active!”, then restart your server. This is due to the way Rails autoloads files in development mode, which affects the plugin and any extensions in the main app (eg: {app_root}/app/models/annotation.rb).

Attributes are NOT case-sensitive! (ie: 'description' and 'Description' will be the same AnnotationAttribute entity and therefore all annotations with those will be the same type od annotation).

TODO: mention how to override controller/models and the purpose of the application controller and application helper and how to get it working in the app.

Due to the way the plugin is set up, the reload behaviour of some files in development mode does not work. Specifically, any changes to the application controller and the application helper require restart of the server.

annotation_add_by_popup_link helper should NOT be used inside a <p> tag since it generates the HTML for the popup box (in a <div>) and places it inline, which would break elements like <p>.

When displaying the values of annotations, ALWAYS 'clean' the data using methods like h (html escape), sanitize and white_list.

By default, duplicate annotations cannot be created (same value for the same attribute, on an annotatable object, regardless of source). For example: a user cannot add a description to a service that matches an existing description for that service.

If you would like to allow duplicate values then use the configuration option: attribute_names_to_allow_duplicates

NOTE: this is different to the limits_per_source config options, which isn't about duplicate annotations, but rather limiting the quantity of annotations of a specific attribute on a specific annotatable object by a specific source.

When creating annotations, symbols (eg: :tag) can be used for attribute names, BUT symbols cannot be used when finding annotations (Strings representing the attribute names can only be used).

To restrict the values for certain annotations, you can either use the Annotations::Config.value_restrictions setting and/or extend the Annotation model in your own codebase (see above), and use the ActiveRecord validates_inclusion_of validation. For the latter, an example is below:

require_dependency RAILS_ROOT + '/vendor/plugins/annotations/lib/app/models/annotation'
 
class Annotation < ActiveRecord::Base
  ...
 
  validates_inclusion_of :value, 
                         :in => [ "fruit", "nut", "fibre" ], 
                         :message => "Please select a valid category.",
                         :if => Proc.new { |ann| ann.attribute_name.downcase == "category" }
 
  ...
end

Dependencies

Plugin: version_fu - versioning library is now embedded in the plugin.

Gem: plugin_test_helper (in order to run the tests for the plugin).

Versioning

Whenever an annotation is updated, a new annotation_version entry is created in the db (corresponding model name = Annotation::Version).

This uses a library from the version_fu plugin - a slightly customised version of this is embedded within the annotations plugin (which won't conflict if version_fu is installed in the main codebase).

Notes:

The “version_creator_id” is only relevant when there are more than one version of an annotation. I.e: for the first version of the annotation the version_creator_id will be nil.

Upgrading The Main Codebase to Annotation Versioning

Shutdown mongrels / servers

Do an svn update (annotation versioning was added to the main codebase in revision 388)

Run db:migrate

Run the ensure_annotations_initial_version.rb script to ensure that the db gets to a consistent state for existing annotations data.

Data Model

Entities

Annotations

Table name: annotations

Fields:

id

source_type

source_id

annotatable_type

annotatable_id

attribute_id

value

value_type

created_at

updated_at

version

version_creator_id

Annotation Versions

Table name: annotation_versions

Fields:

id

annotation_id

version

version_creator_id

source_type

source_id

annotatable_type

annotatable_id

attribute_id

value

value_type

created_at

updated_at

Annotation Attributes

Table name: annotation_attributes

Fields:

id

name

created_at

updated_at

Annotation Value Seeds

Table name: annotation_value_seeds

Fields:

id

attribute_id

value

created_at

updated_at

TODO

Examples

Find annotatable objects that have a specific attribute name AND value:

Gets all annotatables regardless of type:

Annotation.find_annotatables_with_attribute_name_and_value("complexity", "O(x^2)")

Gets only annotatables that are Books:

Book.with_annotations_with_attribute_name_and_value("Tag", "Amusing rhetoric")

Test Scripts in BioCatalogue

What Are Test Scripts?

Test scripts are simple clients to web services which can be uploaded to the BioCatalogue to be run by the BioCatalogue system. The purpose of the test scripts is double fold:

they provide the users with an example client of how to use the service

they enable the biocatalogue system to monitor the status of the service by running these sample clients regularly

Who Can Submit a Test Script?

Only those that have full permissions on services to BioCatalogue are able to submit test scripts as well. They can only submit test scripts against the services which they registered or are responsible for. You can check your user profile on BioCatalogue to see the services you submitted or are responsible for.

What Kinds of Scripts are Allowed?

Test script should be written in one of the following scripting languages:

perl

python

ruby

BioCatalogue is also able to run soapUI project files. These are xml files that can be generated by building test cases with the soapUI framework.

What is the Specification of the Test Scripts?

Test scripts should have the following properties:

Test script files should be executable on the command line and should take no arguments.

Test scripts should always exit with a status code which determines whether the test passed or not. This code is an integer between 0 and 255 (inclusive) where 0 indicates successful execution.

If a script requires other files, these files should supplied with the script. These can be uploaded as a zip archive

Execution time for script should not be more than an hour. Script will be terminated if they exceed this max allowed time

Will Scripts be available for running immediately upon Submission?

Yes. However, newly submitted scripts will be schedule for the next run of the monitoring framework. The BioCatalogue administrators however reserve the right to deactivate any tests if they are deemed to be unsuitable for the monitoring purpose.

Which libraries does BioCatalogue Support?

Perl

The main module needed for WSDL services include :

XML::LibXML

XML::Compile version 1.07

XML::Compile::WSDL11 version 2.08

XML::Compile::SOAP11 version 2.08

Python

PyXML version 0.8.4

fpconst version 0.7.2

ZSI version 2.1

SOAPpy version 0.12.0

MySQLdb

Ruby

ruby version 1.8.6

Example

Perl

Sample perl client for the EMBOSS showfeat service in BioCatalogue.

#!/usr/bin/perl

use XML::Compile::SOAP11;
use XML::Compile::WSDL11;
use XML::Compile::Transport::SOAPHTTP;
use strict;

####

eval {

	my $inputs = {
		'sequence' => { 'usa' => 'embl:X65921'}
	};

	my $serviceendpoint =
	  'http://www.ebi.ac.uk/soaplab/typed/services/display.showfeat';

	print "Retriving and processing the WSDL and the XSDs imported\n";
	my $wsdl  = XML::LibXML->new->parse_file( $serviceendpoint . '?wsdl' );
	my $proxy = XML::Compile::WSDL11->new($wsdl);
	foreach my $schema ( 1, 2, 3 ) {
		my $xsdXml =
		  XML::LibXML->new->parse_file( $serviceendpoint . '?xsd=' . $schema );
		if($XML::Compile::SOAP::VERSION < 2.0)
		{
			$proxy->schemas->importDefinitions($xsdXml);
		}
		else
		{
			$proxy->importDefinitions($xsdXml);
		}
	}

	print "Preparing caller object for runAndWaitFor operation\n";
	my $runAndWaitFor = $proxy->compileClient('runAndWaitFor');

	print "Calling the service and getting the response\n";
	my ( $answer, $trace ) = $runAndWaitFor->( $inputs );

	# &printTrace($trace);

	my %answer = %{$answer};
	my %answer_ = %{ $answer{'runAndWaitForResponse'} };
	my $report = $answer_{'report'};
	my $detailed_status = $answer_{'detailed_status'};
	my $outfile = $answer_{'outfile'};
	my $outfile_url = $answer_{'outfile_url'};


	print "\nSoaplab report received:\n----------------------------\n\n$report\n";

	if ( $detailed_status == 0 ) {
		print "Passed\n";
		exit 0;
	}

	print "Failed\n";
	exit 1;
};

if ($@) {
	print "Caught an exception\n" . $@;
	exit 1;
}

# Print request/response trace
sub printTrace($) {
	my $trace = shift;
	$trace->printTimings;
	$trace->printRequest;
	$trace->printResponse;
}

# File to String
sub file2String($) {
	my $fname = shift;
	open FILE, $fname or die "Couldn't open file: $!";
	my $fcontent = join( "", <FILE> );
	close FILE;
	return $fcontent;
}

References

Embrace Registry Documentation

soapUI Web Services Testing Framework

Proposed BioCatalogue Terms of Use

These Terms of Use are copied from EMBL-EBI services terms of Use

Glossary

User : Person, institution or program using the BioCatalogue

You : refers to the user as defined above

The public services in BioCatalogue available free of charge to be used by any individual and for any purpose except where specific restriction are indicated.

You are free to use BioCatalogue source code consistent with the BSD License

Users of the deployed BioCatalogue services agree not to attempt to use any part of BioCatalogue apart from through the service interfaces provided.

If any single user exploits the BioCatalogue services to a level that prevents, or looks set to prevent, the BioCatalogue providing services to others, the BioCatalogue may discontinue service to that user. BioCatalogue will then contact the user to discuss their needs and how (and if) these can be met. Suggested solutions may include such heavy users licensing for their own in-house use third-party software used in the BioCatalogue services. With permission from the user, the BioCatalogue may divulge their identity to such third parties, and jointly propose possible solutions.

The BioCatalogue does not guarantee the accuracy of any data or software and services for any purpose and accepts no responsibility for consequences of their use.

For planning and scientific review purposes, the BioCatalogue will keep records of usage. BioCatalogue may make information about the total volume of usage of particular software or services available to third parties who supply the services

Logs of usage may also be maintained for the purposes of monitoring and improving services, and measuring the impact a particular service has on our resources. These logs will be kept in confidence and not made available for other purposes or to third parties.

BioCatalogue regards the nature of the work carried out by any individual user as confidential, and shall make every reasonable attempt to prevent breaches of that confidentiality.

BioCatalogue does not accept responsibility for the consequences of any breach of the confidentiality of the BioCatalogue site by third parties who by any means gain illegitimate access to information from BioCatalogue.

BioCatalogue itself places no restrictions on the use or redistribution of the data available via its services. However, some of the original data may be subject to patent, copyright, or other intellectual property rights claimed by third parties. It is the responsibility of users of BioCatalogue services to ensure that their exploitation of the data does not infringe the rights of such third parties. BioCatalogue can neither comment on the validity of their claims nor grant unrestricted permission regarding the use of the data.

BioCatalogue will make all reasonable effort to maintain continuity of service and provide adequate warning of any changes or discontinuities. However, the BioCatalogue accepts no responsibility for the consequences of any temporary or permanent discontinuity in service.

BioCatalogue requires attribution for any of its services or data that it is subsequently used in another product or service.

Any feedback on services and software provided by BioCatalogue will be treated as non-confidential unless the individual or organisation providing the feedback states otherwise.

Relevant law governing these Terms of Use is UK law

Any questions or comments concerning these Terms of Use can be addressed to BioCatalogue.

These Terms of Use reflect the enduring principles under which the BioCatalogue services are offered. We will not, without good reason, alter them, and where alterations are inevitable, we will attempt to give reasonable notice of such alterations. However, we do reserve the right to alter these Terms of Use at any time in order to ensure their appropriateness to the BioCatalogue mission.

BioCatalogue is entering its pilot stage. This pilot is currently in private beta. After passing through a capability and stability review by our early adopters it will be launched as a public beta for wider use in April 2009.

The pilot will support a number of bioinformatics projects and networks, notably EMBRACE and BioSapiens who have temporarily produced service registries. These will be absorbed into the pilot and the BioCatalogue will then takeover from them.

The pilot....

supports user registration and user profiles (for both regular users and service providers). The ability to declare one-self as an “owner” of a service, in order to add testing scripts and so on is [in progress].

covers SOAP services from: DDBJ, EBI, NCBI and community providers such as BioMOBY, EMBRACE and BioSapiens and relevant services sourced from myGrid, SeekDa!. Work on support for DAS and REST services is [in progress].

handles service discovery by keywords or browsing the latest services submitted; filtering of search result by service location, category, provider, technology, usage and so on is [in progress].

supports annotation of services by tags, user comments, rates and text description. Annotated services or their parts (operations, inputs, outputs etc) will then become searchable. Annotations and services will also be harvested from existing registry such as the myGrid Feta registry, EMBRACE, BioMoby, SeekDA but still [in progress].

supports RSS feeds for the latest services submitted and the last updated services [in progress].

exposes an OpenSearch description document.

supports service monitoring by checking the availability of descriptor documents and endpoints as well as using test scripts to check functionality and availability of services [in progress].

To Get Involved

We are looking for early adopters and testers of the BioCatalogue pilot. You can be a service provider, a developer, a bioinformatician or just interested.

Join our mailing list:
BioCatalogue-Friends Mailing List

After the Pilot ...

Integration with myExperiment: on the one hand services from BioCatalogue will be displayed in myExperiment so users of myExperiment can browse them. On the other hand services within workflows in myExperiment will reference the appropriate services in BioCatalogue so users can click through to the information in BioCatalogue.

Integration to Taverna: users will be able to import Web Services and annotations to and from BioCatalogue and Taverna.

Public APIs: RESTful APIs to BioCatalogue.

myBioCatalogue: setup your private BioCatalogue for your project or organisation

For the list of complete features after the pilot see our Roadmap

Current BioCatalogue Terms of Use

Glossary

The BioCatalogue: The website provided at http://www.biocatalogue.org (or “Site”) and other supporting services provided by the BioCatalogue project.

The BioCatalogue Team (or “We”): The provider and management of The BioCatalogue.

User: Person, institution or program using The BioCatalogue.

Member: Person, institution or program who has an account on The BioCatalogue. Members are registered users who may contribute to the content of the Site by registering web services, adding descriptions/tags/etc, rating services, favouriting services and so on. All contributions by Members are identified, and credited, back to them through their BioCatalogue account.

Terms Of Use

Member Accounts

Anyone may sign up for an account and become a Member of The BioCatalogue for free.

All Member profiles are public and therefore can be viewed by anyone and be indexed by search engines such as Google. However, certain private account information like usernames, passwords and registered email addresses are never exposed publicly.

Any personal information provided will be handle in accordance with the United Kingdom's Data Protection legislation. No personal data shall be made public without prior consent from the User.

Content and Services

The BioCatalogue is available free of charge to be used by any individual and for any purpose except where specific restrictions are indicated.

Users of The BioCatalogue agree not to attempt to use any part of The BioCatalogue apart from through the service interfaces provided.

We do not guarantee the accuracy of any data or software and services for any purpose and accept no responsibility for consequences of their use.

Members may submit web services and metadata to The BioCatalogue for free.

Member-posted content, unless source quoted, is licensed under a Creative Commons Public Domain License

The validity and authenticity of the content of any submissions is the sole responsibility of the depositing Members.

We do not guarantee copyrights, patent rights, brand rights, or any other rights belonging to third parties, towards the content appearing on The BioCatalogue.

We decline any responsibility concerning the content and use of other websites and web services reached from The BioCatalogue.

We regard the nature of the work carried out by any individual User as confidential, and shall make every reasonable attempt to prevent breaches of that confidentiality.

We do not accept responsibility for the consequences of any breach of the confidentiality of The BioCatalogue by third parties who by any means gain illegitimate access to information from The BioCatalogue.

We will make all reasonable effort to maintain continuity of The BioCatalogue and provide adequate warning of any changes or discontinuities. However, The BioCatalogue Team accepts no responsibility for the consequences of any temporary or permanent discontinuity to The BioCatalogue.

We place no restrictions on the use or redistribution of the Member-generated content available via The BioCatalogue. However, some of the content may be subject to patent, copyright, or other intellectual property rights claimed by third parties. It is the responsibility of Users of The BioCatalogue to ensure that their exploitation of the data does not infringe the rights of such third parties.

Anyone may use the source code of The BioCatalogue consistent with the BSD License (unless licensed otherwise, in which case the relevant license is applicable).

We require attribution for the use of The BioCatalogue in any subsequent product or service.

Relevant law governing these Terms of Use is UK law. The BioCatalogue is controlled and offered from its facilities in the United Kingdom. We make no representations that The BioCatalogue is appropriate or available for use in other locations. Those who access or use The BioCatalogue from other jurisdictions do so at their own volition and are responsible for compliance with local law.

Withdrawal / Take Down Policy

If any User exploits The BioCatalogue to a level that prevents, or looks set to prevent, The BioCatalogue Team from providing its services to others, We may discontinue some or all services to that User.

If content submitted to The BioCatalogue is deemed illicit, offensive or inappropriate, We reserve the right to immediately remove such content, and permanently withdraw the authorisation to access The BioCatalogue to the User(s) responsible.

If We receive proof of copyright violation or plagiarism, the relevant content will be removed immediately.

Content may be withdrawn from The BioCatalogue at the request of the provider / copyright holder.

A notice of withdrawal will accompany any withdrawal of content by The BioCatalogue Team to the author of the content, together with the reason for such withdrawal.

Where the reason for take down or withdrawal is found to be unsubstantiated the content may be re-exposed into The BioCatalogue, with any appropriate amendments to the content itself or access arrangements.

Preservation

For planning and scientific review purposes, We will keep records of usage and other metrics. We may use this information, together with information from the content of The BioCatalogue in presentations, reports and other project material, in the accordance with the Data Protection Act.

We may make information about particular software or web services available to third parties who supply the services, in the accordance with the Data Protection Act.

Logs of usage may also be maintained for the purposes of monitoring and improving The BioCatalogue, and measuring the impact a particular service has on our resources. These logs will be kept in confidence and not made available to third parties.

Any feedback on The BioCatalogue will be treated as non-confidential unless the individual or organisation providing the feedback states otherwise.

Withdrawn and deleted content are not removed permanently from The BioCatalogue, but are removed from public view and public consumption (including removed from the BioCatalogue search). However, they may still exist in backups and other operational data stores, and also exist in internet caches and search engines.

These Terms of Use reflect the enduring principles under which The BioCatalogue are offered. We will not, without good reason, alter them, and where alterations are inevitable, we will attempt to give reasonable notice of such alterations. However, we do reserve the right to alter these Terms of Use at any time in order to ensure their appropriateness to the BioCatalogue mission.

Any questions or comments concerning these Terms of Use can be addressed to the BioCatalogue Team.

Previous BioCatalogue Terms of Use

These Terms of Use are based on the EMBL-EBI services terms of Use

Glossary

User : Person, institution or program using the BioCatalogue

You : refers to the user as defined above

The public services in BioCatalogue available free of charge to be used by any individual and for any purpose except where specific restriction are indicated.

You are free to use BioCatalogue source code consistent with the BSD License

Users of the deployed BioCatalogue services agree not to attempt to use any part of BioCatalogue apart from through the service interfaces provided.

If any single user exploits the BioCatalogue services to a level that prevents, or looks set to prevent, the BioCatalogue providing services to others, the BioCatalogue may discontinue service to that user. BioCatalogue will then contact the user to discuss their needs and how (and if) these can be met. Suggested solutions may include such heavy users licensing for their own in-house use third-party software used in the BioCatalogue services. With permission from the user, the BioCatalogue may divulge their identity to such third parties, and jointly propose possible solutions.

The BioCatalogue does not guarantee the accuracy of any data or software and services for any purpose and accepts no responsibility for consequences of their use.

For planning and scientific review purposes, the BioCatalogue will keep records of usage. BioCatalogue may make information about the total volume of usage of particular software or services available to third parties who supply the services

Logs of usage may also be maintained for the purposes of monitoring and improving services, and measuring the impact a particular service has on our resources. These logs will be kept in confidence and not made available for other purposes or to third parties.

BioCatalogue regards the nature of the work carried out by any individual user as confidential, and shall make every reasonable attempt to prevent breaches of that confidentiality.

BioCatalogue does not accept responsibility for the consequences of any breach of the confidentiality of the BioCatalogue site by third parties who by any means gain illegitimate access to information from BioCatalogue.

BioCatalogue itself places no restrictions on the use or redistribution of the data available via its services. However, some of the original data may be subject to patent, copyright, or other intellectual property rights claimed by third parties. It is the responsibility of users of BioCatalogue services to ensure that their exploitation of the data does not infringe the rights of such third parties. BioCatalogue can neither comment on the validity of their claims nor grant unrestricted permission regarding the use of the data.

BioCatalogue will make all reasonable effort to maintain continuity of service and provide adequate warning of any changes or discontinuities. However, the BioCatalogue accepts no responsibility for the consequences of any temporary or permanent discontinuity in service.

BioCatalogue requires attribution for any of its services or data that it is subsequently used in another product or service.

Any feedback on services and software provided by BioCatalogue will be treated as non-confidential unless the individual or organisation providing the feedback states otherwise.

Relevant law governing these Terms of Use is UK law

Any questions or comments concerning these Terms of Use can be addressed to BioCatalogue.

These Terms of Use reflect the enduring principles under which the BioCatalogue services are offered. We will not, without good reason, alter them, and where alterations are inevitable, we will attempt to give reasonable notice of such alterations. However, we do reserve the right to alter these Terms of Use at any time in order to ensure their appropriateness to the BioCatalogue mission.